<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The christian doctrine in manner of a dialogue betweene the master and the disciple Made by the Reuer. Fa. Iames Ledesma of the Society of Iesus. Now lately translated into English, for the vse of children, and other vnlearned Catholickes</title>
            <author>Ledisma, Jacobus, 1519-1575.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05220</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15353</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106750</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842460</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842460</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7113</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05220)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7113)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 473:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The christian doctrine in manner of a dialogue betweene the master and the disciple Made by the Reuer. Fa. Iames Ledesma of the Society of Iesus. Now lately translated into English, for the vse of children, and other vnlearned Catholickes</title>
                  <author>Ledisma, Jacobus, 1519-1575.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Fr. Garnet's second press?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1597.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation from the original by Jacobus Ledisma.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from and press conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Catechisms.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7113:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7113:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHRISTIAN DOCTRINE in manner of Dialogue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the
Maſter and the Diſciple</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Made by the Reuer. Fa. Iames Ledeſma of the Society of
Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now lately tranſlated into Engliſh, for the vſe of children,
and other vnlearned Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes.</p>
            <p>1597.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="alphabets">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7113:2"/>
               <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> a. b. c. d. e. f. g. h. i. k. l. m. n. o. p. q.
r. ſ. s. t. v. u. w. x. y. z. &amp;.</p>
            <p>A. B. C. D. E. F. G. H. I. K. L. M N. O. P. Q. R. S. T. V. W. X.
Y. Z</p>
            <p>
               <hi>a. b. c. d. e. f. g. h. i. k. l. m. n. o. p. q. r. ſ. s. t.
v. uw. x. y. z. &amp;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. B. C. D. E. F. G. H. I. K. L. M N. O. P. Q. R. S. T. V. W.
X. Y. Z</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ab. eb. ib. ob. ub. ac. ec. ic. oc. uc. ad. ed. id. od. ud. ba.
be. bi. bo. bu da. de. di. do. du fa. fe. fi. fo. fu.</p>
            <p>1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. 11. 12.</p>
            <p>I. II. III. IIII. V. VI. VII. VII. IX. X. XI. XII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:7113:2"/>
            <head>IESVS MARIA.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>OF the name and ſigne of a Chriſtian. <hi>Chap.
1.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Are you a Chriſtian?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, by the grace of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What is a Chriſtian?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>The Diſciple of Chriſt: that is he which hauing bene
baptized be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth and maketh open profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion of his law.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What do you vnderſtand Chriſt to be?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>He is trew God and trew man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Which is the ſigne of a Chriſtian?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>The ſigne of the holy Croſſe, which is made by putting
the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d <pb n="4" facs="tcp:7113:3"/> vnto the head, &amp; vnder the breaſt, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
at the lefte ſhoulder, and the right, ſaying. In the name of the Father and
of the Sonne &amp; of the holy Ghoſt. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Why is it made in this manner?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>To ſignifie vnto vs two great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries. the one of the
moſt holy Trinity: the other of the Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt
who died for vs vpon the Croſſe.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the end of man and neceſſary things for a Chriſtian.
<hi>Chap. 2.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>For what end was man created?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>For to loue and ſerue God in this life: and afterward, for
to ſee him and enioy him in the other life.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>How many thinges are neceſſary for a Chriſtian that he
may attaine his end, and be ſaued?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:7113:3"/>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Fower. Faith, Hope, Charity, &amp; good workes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What do you beleeue by Faith?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>All that which the holy Catholick Roman Church beleeueth &amp;
hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth: and principally, that which is contained in the Creed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Say the Creed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1 Credo in Deum Patrem omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentem, creatorem
coeli &amp; terrae.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2 Et in Ieſum Chriſtum, filium eius vnicum,
Dominum noſtrum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3 Qui conceptus est de ſpiritu ſancto natus ex
Maria Virgine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4 Paſſus ſub Pontio Pilato, crucifix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,
mortuus &amp; ſepultus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5 Deſcendit ad inferos, tertia die reſurrexit a
mortuis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6 Aſcendit ad coelos, ſedet ad dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram Dei
patris omnipotentis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7 Inde venturus est iudicare viuos &amp;
mortuos.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:7113:4"/>
                     <hi>8 Gredo in Spiritum
ſanctum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9 Sanctam Eccleſiam Catholicam, Sanctorum
communionem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10 Remiſſionem peccatorum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11 Carnis reſurrectionem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12 Vitam aeternam. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1 I Beleeue in God the Father Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, maker of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
&amp; earth.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 And in Ieſus Chriſt, his onely Sonne our Lord.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Which was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, borne of the
Virgine Mary.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Suffered vnder Pontius Pilate, was crucified, dead and
buried.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 He deſcended into Hel, the third day he roſe
againe from the dead.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 He aſcended into Heauen, and ſitteth at the right
hand of God the Father Almighty.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 From thence he ſhall come to iudge the quicke and
the dead.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:7113:4"/>8 I beleeue in the holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p n="9">9 The holy Catholicke Church: the communion of
Saintes.</p>
                  <p n="10">10 The forgiueneſſe of Sinnes.</p>
                  <p n="11">11 The reſurrection of the fleſh.</p>
                  <p n="12">12 And the life euerlaſting. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>OF the Creed <hi>Chap. 3.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What haue we ſaied?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>The Creed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Who made it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>The twelue Apoſtles, whan they were to go for to preach the
goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell through all the world.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Wherfore did they make it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>For to inſtruct vs in Faith.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What is conteined in the Creed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Twelue articles: that is, twelue principall partes of our
faith.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:7113:5"/>
               <head>An expoſition of ſome principall articles of the Creede.
<hi>Chap. 4.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>In whome do you beleeue?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>I beleeue in God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What is God?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>He is the Creatour and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of heauen and earth, and
Lord of all thinges.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Why is God ſaid to be almighty?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe with his very will onely and infinite power he can
make and deſtroy euery thing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What do you beleeue that the moſt holy Trinity is?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>It is that very ſame God, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Sonne, &amp; the
holy ghoſt three perſons, &amp; one onely God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Is the Father God?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea forſooth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Is the Sonne God?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:7113:5"/>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea forſooth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Is the holy ghoſt God?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea forſooth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Be there three Gods?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>No forſooth. For although there be three perſons, yet is
there but one onely God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſimilitude can you geue me of the moſt holy
Trinity?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Euen as we that are made accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his image and
likeneſſe, haue one onely ſoule, and three powers therof: memory,
vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Do you beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea forſooth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What do you thinke Ieſus Chriſt to be?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>He is the Sonne of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: altogither as mighty, as
wiſe as good as the Father, which So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God became man for vs in the wombe
of the gloriouſe Virgine <pb n="10" facs="tcp:7113:6"/> Mary, by the worke of the holy
Ghoſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What other thinge hath Chriſt done for vs?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>He was borne of the ſame Virgin Mary, ſhe remaining a
Virgin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her childbirth, in her child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birth, and after her
childbirth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>And what more?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>He was crucified dead and buried deſcended into hell, the
third day he roſe againe from the dead. He aſcended into heauen and
ſitteth at the right hand of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther almighty, as his ſonne: and
fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence he ſhall come to iudge the quicke and the dead, for to render to
euery one according to his workes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Do you beleue in the holy ghoſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea forſooth, for he is trew God, and the third perſon of
the moſt holy Trinitye: whoe geueth his <pb n="11" facs="tcp:7113:6"/> grace and his
giftes to the holy Catholicke Church.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What is the holye Catholicke Church?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>It is the wholle congregation of the faithfull Chriſtians,
who haue and confeſſe the faith of Ieſus Chriſt: the head of which
Church is Chriſt him ſelfe, and the Pope his Vicar on earth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What good haue we in the Church?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>This: that we are partakers of all the ſacrifices,
Sacramentes, and good workes which are donne therin: And we haue the
remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinnes, with many other graces and giftes of God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What is the reſurrection of the fleſhe, and the life
euerlaſting?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>It is, that at the day of iudgement euery one ſhall riſe
againe with the very ſame body &amp; ſoule: and <pb n="12" facs="tcp:7113:7"/> the
good ſhall go into euerlaſting life, for to ſee &amp; enioy God: and the
euell vnto Hell, with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uells.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Who goeth to the paines of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>The ſoules of thoſe which dye in the grace of God, and
haue not fully ſatisfied for their ſinnes: and after that they haue
ſuffered the dew puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts they ſhall go to heauen.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>OF the ſecond thing neceſſary for a Chriſtian that
is, of Hope. <hi>Chap. 5.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What do you looke to haue by Hope in God?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>The life euerlaſting: which prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally is obteined by the
grace of <pb n="13" facs="tcp:7113:7"/> God, and beſides, by the merittes which through
the ſame grace proceed from vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>For to obteine that which wee hope for, what is required?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Amongſt other thinges, Prayer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What prayers doth the Chruch teach vs?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>The Pater noſter, the Aue Mary, and the Salue Regina, and
others.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Say the Pater noſter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1 Pater noſter qui es in coelis: ſancti ficetur
nomen tuum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2 Adueniat regnum tuum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3 Fiat voluntas tua, ſicut in coelo, et in
terra.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4 Panem noſtrum quotidianum da nobis
hodie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5 Et dimitte nobis debita noſtra, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut et nos
dimittimus debitoribus noſtris.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6 Et ne nos inducas in tentationem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:7113:8"/>
                     <hi>7 Sed libera nos a malo.
Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Our Father which art in Heauen</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Hallowed be thy name.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Thy kingdome come.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thy will be done in earth, as it is in heauen.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Giue vs this day our daily bread.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 And forgiue vs our treſpaſſes, as we forgiue
them that treſpaſſe againſt vs.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 And lead vs not into temptation.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 But deliuer vs from euell. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>OF the Pater noſter. <hi>Chap. 6</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What haue we ſaied?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>The <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Who made it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: &amp; he ſpoke it with his moſt
holy mouth and <pb n="15" facs="tcp:7113:8"/> gaue it to his Diſciples and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it
is the moſt excellent of all praiers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What do we aske in this praier?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Firſt we aske the glory of God, and than our owne good for
our ſoule, and body, and that he will deliuer vs from all euell.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>With whome do we ſpeake ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>With our Lord God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Where is God?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>He is in euery place: but he is ſaid principally to be in
heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: where he doth manifeſt him ſelfe vnto the Bleſſed.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>OF the Aue Mary. <hi>Chap. 7</hi>
               </head>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aue Maria gratia plena, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus tecum. Benedicta tu in
mulieri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus: <pb n="16" facs="tcp:7113:9"/> et benedictus fructus ventris tui, Ieſus.
Sancta Maria, mater Dei, ora pro nobis peccatoribus nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c et in hora mortis
noſtrae. Amen.</hi>
                  </p> 
                  <p>Haile Mary, full of grace, our Lord is with thee, bleſſed
arte thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong women, and bleſſed is the fruite of thy wombe, Ieſus.
Holy Mary, mother of God, pray for vs ſinners, now, and in the houre of our
death. Amen.</p>
               </q>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What haue we ſaied?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>The Aue Mary.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Who made it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>The Angell Gabriel, when he came to ſalute our Lady:
wherun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to are adioined ſome wordes of S. Elizabeth and of the Church.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>With whome do we ſpeake in the Aue Mary?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>With our Lady.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What do you beleeue our Lady to be?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:7113:9"/>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>She is mother of God, a Virgin, full of grace, and of all
vertew: Queene of heauen, and of earth, and our aduocate.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Where is our Lady?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>She is in heauen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſay you of her which is in the Church?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>That is the Image of her which is in heauen, for to put vs in
mind of her: and becauſe it is her image, we do reuerence vnto it, in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
of her ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>As there are many Images of our Lady, be there alſo many
Ladies?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>No forſooth: but one only which is in heauen: whome thoſe
Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges doe repreſent which are on earth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Why than is ſhee called, our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Pity, of Remedy, of
Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and in other like ſorte?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>For the many and diuerſe bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fittes <pb n="18" facs="tcp:7113:10"/>
which ſhe doth vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What do we ſay to her in the Aue Mary?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>We ſalute her and praiſe her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending our ſelues
vnto her.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>OF the Salue Regina. <hi>Chap. 8.</hi>
               </head>
               <q>SAlue Regina, mater miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diae, vita, dulcedo, et ſpes
noſtra, ſalue: Ad te clamamus, exules, filij Euae: Ad te ſuſpiramus,
gementes, et flentes, in hac lachrimaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> valle. Eia ergo aduocata noſtra,
illos tuos miſericordes oculos ad nos conuerte. Et Ieſum benedictum fructum
ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris tui nobis poſt hoc exilium oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. O clemens: Opia: O dulcis
Vir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>go Maria. Ora pro nobis ſancta Dei genetrix: vt digni efficiamur
promiſſionibus Chriſti.</q>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:7113:10"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What haue we ſaied?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>The Salue Regina.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Who taught it vs?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Our holy mother the Church.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>To whome do we ſpeake?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>With the ſame Virgin Mary.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What do we ſay vnto her in it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Other praiſes of the ſame Virgin, demaunding with all her
holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and helpe.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>OF other praiers and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation of Saintes. <hi>Chap.
9.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>After the Virgin Mary haue you deuotion to other Saintes?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea forſooth, vnto all, as vnto the frendes of God, and our
inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours in heauen: but eſpecially vnto my Agnell keeper, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the Saint of my name.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:7113:11"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>And vnto the Relickes of Saints?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>I honour them alſo, becauſe they haue bene the temple of
the holy Ghoſt, and are to be reunited to their gloriouſe ſoules.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What Prayer do you make vnto them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Thoſe which the Church doth teach vs, &amp; alſo for their
honour, and that they may pray for me, I ſay the Pater noſter and Aue
Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What doe you whan you go to bedd?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Two thinges. Firſt, hauing made the ſigne of the
Croſſe, I examine my conſcience. Secondlye I ſay the generall
Confeſſion, the Pater noſter, and the Aue Mary, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my
deuotions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>How do you examine your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience?</p>
               </sp>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:7113:11"/>
                  <head>OF the examining of our Conſcience.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Firſt I thanke God for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitts receiued,
eſpecially that day.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <p>What more?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Than I thinke of my ſinnes, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of that day,
being ſory for them, with purpoſe of amending and of confeſſing
them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <p>What than?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Finally, I aske God pardon, and make a firme purpoſe of
ſinning no more.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <p>And what do you the mornings?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Three things. Firſt, I thanke God that he hath kept me
that night, and for his other benefitts.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the ſecond thing you do?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>I offer him my body and ſoule.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the third?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>I beſeech him that whatſoeuer I ſhall do may be for
his holy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: <pb n="22" facs="tcp:7113:12"/> and alſo I ſay other my
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotions mentall and vocall: that is, with the minde, and with the voice.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>OF the third thing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for a Chriſtian which is
Charity. <hi>Chap. 10.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Which is the third thing neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for a Chriſtian?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Charity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Whome ought we to loue with charity?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>God aboue all thinges, and our neighbour as our ſelues, for
the loue of God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſhall we loue our neighbour as our ſelues?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Deſiring for him, and doing vnto him, that which we would
for our <pb n="23" facs="tcp:7113:12"/> ſelues, according vnto reaſon, and the law of
God.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>OF the fourth thing neceſſary for a Chriſtian that is
of good workes. <hi>Chap. 11.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Which is the fourth thing nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſary for a
Chriſtian?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Good workes. for after that one is come to the yeares of
diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, faith is not ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t without good workes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What good workes are theſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Thoſe which are ordained in the tenne commaundements of God,
and in the other of the Church, with the workes of mercy, and of other
vertewes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Say the tenne Commandements.</p>
               </sp>
               <q>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:7113:13"/> 
                  <p n="1">1 I am thy Lord God. Thou ſhalt haue no other Gods but
me.</p> 
                  <p n="2">2 Thou ſhalt not take the name of God in vaine.</p> 
                  <p n="3">3 Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber to ſanctifie the holy daies.</p> 
                  <p n="4">4 Honour thy Father and mother.</p> 
                  <p n="5">5 Thou ſhalt not kill.</p> 
                  <p n="6">6 Thou ſhalt not committ aduoutry.</p> 
                  <p n="7">7 Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</p> 
                  <p n="8">8 Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe.</p> 
                  <p n="9">9 Thou ſhalt not deſire thy neighbours wife.</p> 
                  <p n="10">10 Thou ſhalt not deſire thy neighbours
goods.</p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>AN expoſition of the ten Commaundements. <hi>Chap.
12.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Where did God geue theſe tenne Commaundements?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Firſt in the ould lawe. and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <pb n="25" facs="tcp:7113:13"/>
Chriſt our Lord confirmed them in the new.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What is conteined in them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>The three firſt, of worſhiping one God, of not taking his
name in vaine, and of ſanctifying the holy daies: do apperteine to the honor
of God. becauſe he is to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, firſt, with the hart, than with the
tongue, and with deeds.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>And the other ſeuen?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>They apperteine to the profitt of our neighbour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe tenne commaundements in how many are they
comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>In the two precepts of Charity: that is, to loue God aboue all
thinges, and our neighbour as our ſelues.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>So that the wholle law of God is comprehended in this ſweet
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte of loue, which our Lorde <pb n="26" facs="tcp:7113:14"/> graunt vs for his
infinite goodnes. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>OF the Commaundements of the Church. <hi>Chap.
13.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Say the Commaundements of the Church.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p n="1">1 To heare Maſſe on the holy daies commaunded,</p>
                  <p n="2">2 To faſt the Lent and other daies commaunded, and to
abſtaine from fleſh on the accuſtomed daies.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 To go to Confeſſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> at the leaſt, once a
yeare.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 To Receaue at the leaſt at Eaſter.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 To pay tithes.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>OF the ſeuen Capitall ſinnes, which are called mortall.
<hi>Chap. 14.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:7113:14"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>We haue ſpoken of the good workes which are to be donne. Say
now the euell which muſt be ſhunned: and firſt of the ſeuen ſinnes,
which are called mortall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p> 
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1 Pride</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2 Couetouſnes</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>3 Lechery</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>4 Anger</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>5 Gluttony</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>6 Enuy</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>7 Slouth.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe are cauſe and heades of all other, and therfore are
called Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall: although ſometimes they may be veniall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What is Sinne?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>It is that which is thought, ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or donne contrary to
the law and will of God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What harme doth mortall ſinne to the ſinner?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>It maketh him looſe God and his grace, and the glory which
was promiſed him: &amp; maketh him det<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour of the euerlaſting paine of
Hell.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:7113:15"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Why is it called mortall?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe it killeth the ſoule, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it to looſe the
life of grace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What doth veniall ſinne?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>It cauſeth not the loſſe of Gods grace, neither
deſerueth hell: but it maketh a man to waxe colde in the loue and ſeruice
of God, and meriteth temporall puniſhment, and diſpoſeth alſo vnto
mortall ſinne.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>OF the ſeuen Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of our holy mother the Church.
<hi>Chap. 15.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What other thing is neceſſary for vs?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>It is neceſſary that we know the holy Sacraments, and that
we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them in dew time wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our holy mother the Church ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth 
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:7113:15"/> and declareth vnto vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>For what end?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>For the blotting out of our ſinnes and the obteining Gods
grace, and helpe for the doing of good workes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Say the Sacraments of our holy mother the Church. 
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1 Baptiſme</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2 Confirmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           </hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>3 Euchariſt</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>4 Penance</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>5 Extreme vnction</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>6 Holy orders</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>7 Matrimony.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>AN expoſition of ſome Sacraments. <hi>Chap.
16.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Who hath ordained theſe Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Wherfore?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>For to geue vs pardon of our ſinns and to communicate vnto
vs his grace, and the meritts of his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion. <pb n="30" facs="tcp:7113:16"/> and in
euery one there is geuen grace for ſome particuler thing, but it is required
that we receiue them worthely.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What effect hath the Sacrament of Baptiſme?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>It maketh vs Chriſtians, and the chrildren of God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>How is this brought to paſſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe we are all borne in origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſinne: which
togither with all other ſinnes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted before Bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme, is taken away by
the ſame: and there is geuen vs Gods grace and other his giftes: And ſo we
are made children of God, and heires of euerlaſting life.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>For what effect ſerueth the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Confeſſion or
Penance?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>That God our Lord may pardon our ſinnes which we haue donne
after Baptiſme.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>How muſt he prepare him ſelfe, <pb n="31" facs="tcp:7113:16"/> that
will be confeſſed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>He muſt do three thinges. Firſt, he muſt procure with
diligence to to call to mind his ſinnes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, to haue ſorow and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance with purpoſe of
ſinning no more.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, he muſt make a full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of them all,
and fulfill his penance geuen him by his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>For what effect ſerueth the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Aultar?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Firſt, that our ſoule may be nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and fedd with
the grace of God and vnited vnto him.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, that we fall not eaſely into ſinne.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, for to obteine all perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Who is in the Bleſſed Sacrament?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde: in body, <pb n="32" facs="tcp:7113:17"/>
ſoule, and Godhead, euen as he is in heauen: as well in the hoſte, as in
the chalice: after the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Prieſt, which is made in the
Maſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What is the Maſſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>It is a memory and trew repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the life,
paſſion, &amp; death of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. and it is with all a
Sacrifice where Chriſt him ſelfe is offered for the quicke and the dead.
And therfore we muſt be preſent therat, with great deuotion and
attention.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>How muſt one prepare him ſelfe to receaue worthely the
Bleſſed Sacrament?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>By going with deuotion without conſcience of mortall
ſinne, and being firſt confeſſed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>For what effectes do the other ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments ſerue?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>For to receiue diuerſe graces of <pb n="33" facs="tcp:7113:17"/> God,
for that end, for the which they were ordained.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>OF the other things which appertaine to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
doctrine, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to good workes. <hi>Chap. 17.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Say the other thinges which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to good workes, or to the
Chriſtian doctrine, and firſt the three theologicall vertewes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Faith, Hope, and Charity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Say the fower Cardinall vertewes</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p> 
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Prudence.</item>
                        <item>2 Fortitude.</item>
                        <item>3 Iuſtice.</item>
                        <item>4 Temperance.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Say the ſeuen giftes of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p> 
                     <list>
                        <item>1 The gifte of wiſdome.</item>
                        <item>2 of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</item>
                        <item>3 of Counſell.</item>
                        <item>4 of Fortitude.</item>
                        <item>5 of Knowledge.</item>
                        <item>6 <pb n="34" facs="tcp:7113:18"/> of Piety.</item>
                        <item>7 And the gifte of the feare of God.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Say the eight Beatitudes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p n="1">1 Bleſſed are the poore of ſpirite, for theirs is
the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Bleſſed are the meeke: for they ſhall
poſſeſſe the earth.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Bleſſed are they that mourne: for they ſhall be
comfourted.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Bleſſed are they that hunger &amp; thirſt after
Iuſtice, for they ſhall haue their fill.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 Bleſſed are the mercifull: for they ſhall
obtaine mercy.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 Bleſſed are the cleane of hart, for they ſhall
ſee God.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 Bleſſed are the peace-makers, for they ſhall be
called the children of God.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 Bleſſed are they that ſuffer perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution for
Iuſtice, for theirs is the Kingdome of heauen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:7113:18"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Say the twelue fruites of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p> 
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Charity.</item>
                        <item>2 Ioy.</item>
                        <item>3 Peace.</item>
                        <item>4 Patience.</item>
                        <item>5 Longanimity.</item>
                        <item>6 Goodnes.</item>
                        <item>7 Benignity.</item>
                        <item>8 Meeknes.</item>
                        <item>9 Faith.</item>
                        <item>10 Modeſty.</item>
                        <item>11 Continency.</item>
                        <item>12 Chaſtity.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Say the ſeuen workes of mercy corporall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p> 
                     <list>
                        <item>1 To feed the hungry.</item>
                        <item>2 To geue drinke to the thirſty.</item>
                        <item>3 To cloth the naked.</item>
                        <item>4 To harbour Pilgrimes.</item>
                        <item>5 To viſitt the ſicke.</item>
                        <item>6 To viſitt Priſoners.</item>
                        <item>7 To bury the Dead.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Say the ſeuen workes of mercy ſpirituall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p> 
                     <list>
                        <item>1 To geue good Counſell to other.</item>
                        <item>2 To inſtruct the ignorant.</item>
                        <item>3 To admoniſh thoſe which ſinne.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="36" facs="tcp:7113:19"/>4 To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort the afflicted &amp;
troubled</item>
                        <item>5 To pardon offences &amp; iniuries re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</item>
                        <item>6 To beare patiently the trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomnes of
others.</item>
                        <item>7 To pray for the quicke and dead.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Say the fifteene miſteries of the life of our Lord Ieſus
Chriſt, for to meditate and ſay the Roſary of our Lady.</p>
                  <p>And firſt the fiue ioyfull.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p> 
                     <list>
                        <item>1 The Annunciation of our Lady whan the Sonne of God
was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</item>
                        <item>2 The viſitation of Saint Elizabeth.</item>
                        <item>3 The natiuity of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt.</item>
                        <item>4 The Preſentation of our Lord in the Temple.</item>
                        <item>5 Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our Lord was found againe in the Temple
amongſt the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:7113:19"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Say now the fiue ſorowfull.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p> 
                     <list>
                        <item>1 The Prayer of our Lorde in the garden.</item>
                        <item>2 The whipping at the pillar.</item>
                        <item>3 The Crowning with a crowne of thornes.</item>
                        <item>4 The carying of the Croſſe vnto Mount
Caluary.</item>
                        <item>5 The crucifying and Death of the Croſſe.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Say the fiue gloriouſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p> 
                     <list>
                        <item>1 The Reſurrection of our Lorde.</item>
                        <item>2 His aſcenſion vnto heauen.</item>
                        <item>3 The comming of the holy Ghoſt.</item>
                        <item>4 The Aſſumption of our Lady.</item>
                        <item>5 Her Coronation aboue all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells and Saintes.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:7113:20"/>Whan it ringeth to the <hi>Aue Mary,</hi> we
may obtaine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence by ſaying: 
<q> 
                     <p> 
                        <label>At the firſt toll.</label> 
                        <hi>Angelus Domini
runciauit Mariae et concepit de ſpiritu ſancto.</hi>
                     </p> 
                     <p>Aue Maria. &amp;c.</p> 
                     <p> 
                        <label>At the ſecond toll.</label> 
                        <hi>Ecce Ancilla Domini,
fiat mihi ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum verbum tuum.</hi>
                     </p> 
                     <p>Aue Maria. &amp;c.</p> 
                     <p> 
                        <label>At the third toll.</label> 
                        <hi>Et verbum caro factum
eſt, et habitauit in nobis.</hi>
                     </p> 
                     <p>Aue Maria. &amp;c.</p> 
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Oremus.</head>
               <p>GRatiam tuam quaſumus Domine me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tibus noſtris infunde, vt
qui An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelo nunciante Chriſti filij tui incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem <pb n="39" facs="tcp:7113:20"/>
cognouimus: per Paſſionem eius et crucem ad Reſurrectionis gloriam
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducamur: Per eundem Chriſtum Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num noſtrum. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Praier before ſtudy.</head>
               <p>CLementiſſime Pater, infunde nobis per meritu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſu
Chriſti filij tui Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus ſancti gratiam, qua intellectus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
liberalibus diſciplinis plenius illuſtre tur, quas in diuinum tuum honorem
ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando, et noſtram ſpiritualem vtilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem conuertere poſſimus. Per
Chriſtum Dominum noſtrum. Amen.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:7113:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:7113:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
